Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and this
is gonna be part two of our
introduction to Organic Chemistry.
Now in organic, one of the big
things that we're gonna be looking
at in this particular class, or
any course on organic chemistry
is the story of functional groups.
Now what are they exactly?
Well, these are special subs or branches
that are attached to our parent chain.
And the whole idea with these is that
they really define the properties
and behaviors of the molecules.
And they define all the different types
of reactions that they are capable of
partaking in as we are gonna see them.
So let's take a look at all of our
different functional groups and try
to understand a little bit about
them and what they look like so that
way you can start memorizing them
for your organic chemistry class.
And so that way when you do
labs, Our learning about them.
They'll make a little bit
more sense as you go forward.
Now, before we continue on to our
functional groups, we must go over some
common abbreviations that you are going to
be seeing in the next part of this video
or throughout an organic chemistry class.
The first one is the letter R, which
is commonly placed on different
structures or functional groups.
All that means is it represents
the rest of the molecule.
So for example, if I have, uh, a ch a
molecule that looks like this and I say
R-X, well, what exactly does that mean?
Well, R is generally, like I said,
the rest of the molecule, which
could be something as simple as,
let's say it could be an alkyl chain.
Like for example, we have a
butane here with an X group.
It could be any type of chain.
Now, what about X?
Well, X is a halogen.
It's something that comes
from introductory chemistry.
We commonly will use an X just
to say, it could be chlorine,
bromine, chlorine, iodine.
It doesn't exactly matter in that
situation, but it is a halogen,
which is a reactive chemical.
So this is something, if you do see
'em, it's just referring to A or R.
It's a larger molecule.
Let's go onto to our functional groups.
This first one is alkenes.
Alkenes, we went over in part one.
This is anything that is involving
a double bonded structure.
So if we have C with C with a double
bond, and that is connected to let's say
hydrogens, or even if it's connected to.
Another chain.
It has that double bonded structure,
which is the key thing that we are looking
for in any of those types of examples.
Um, another type of example of a
structural formula with this is, let's
say I have my rest of my molecule.
It has that CC double bond within the
structure, and we want to show that it has
other key little traits with it as well.
The whole entire thing that we are
looking for as we are, are trying to
represent these structures is that we
have that double bondage structure onto
our next, our next group is the alkins.
Alkins are what have a triple
bonded structure, so we're
looking for the C triple bond c.
And a different example of this is, let's
say if I have my, a very long chain, if
it's going like CH three, CH two, and then
all of a sudden I have C with a triple
bond in the middle of the structure, this
is representing an alkin just like this.
You could also represent that as
a,  Geometric shape as well, just
like, so,  where you have the
same exact structure behind that.
And let's make sure this is correct.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
As you can see, I'm counting my carbons
as I am drawing all those little pieces.
So that is a big important part
of as you're going through the
chemistry, is counting carbons.
Our next one is an Alkyl halide,
which as you can see from this
one, we are using that R group.
As well as that,  X for
a halide or halogen.
So this just means that we have a al
alcohol chain attached to a either
chlorine or bromine, uh, or iodine.
So for example, if I just draw
a propane here with a chlorine
on it, we have chloro propane.
This would be an example if we are
to draw another type of chain where
let's say I have a bromine attached.
That would be another example.
You might also just commonly see an X
telling you that you have a halogen on it.
There are many different
types of examples.
Alcohols are a common functional
group that we see in our everyday
lives, whether it's at maybe on
a weekend or it's in the kitchen.
We commonly see alcohols all around us.
Uh, alcohols are always denoted
by the oh group that is on that
which is your hydroxyl group.
So this denotes that we have an alcohol.
So like I mentioned, hydroxyl,
uh, telling you you have that, OH,
attachment on it or an alcohol.
Um, with this one, it's
the same idea as before.
If I have a chain with an -OH
on it, Or potentially a ring
structure with an with an OH on it.
That's letting you know we
have an alcohol structure.
Our next functional group is an ether.
The thing about an ether is that
you notice that there's an oxygen
holding hands with a different
functional group on both sides.
So with this, it doesn't have to
necessarily be the same exact Alco group.
You'll commonly notice that
someone will draw all maybe an
R with an apostrophe next to it.
That's letting you know that
the chains do not have to match.
So if you see R Prime or R Double
Prime, triple Prime, this is
telling you that all the groups are
different, um, as they're being shown.
So Ether is always joining
two pieces together.
So if I were to draw an example of
this, this could be like this one
here where we have dimethyl ether,
or we could try to expand that.
Let's say if I made it where we have our,
uh, geometric structures and we could see
that, okay, both of them are not the same.
We have one that has two carbons on it.
Then the other one over on the
far side has three carbons on it.
So each one of them is different.
Thiols are a major part
of more into biochemistry.
We do see them in organic.
They're responsible for a lot of aromas,
generally stuff that's very  pungent.
So thiols are, um, are the
one type of molecule you'll
see with a sulfur atom on it.
They also bond to two things, just
like oxygen being that they're part of
the same group right below each other.
So with these, typically you will
see, uh, just a little sulfur
attached to the side of a chain.
Uh, just like before, uh, they do
not necessarily have to only be at
that first position, but they could
also be at the second one as well.
And these are your thighs with ketones.
These are your first species that have
a carbon double bonded to an oxygen.
Oxygen needs two bonds.
Notice how we have a double bond here.
What that does is if it fulfills its
requirement of needing those two bonds.
So you either see oxygen in the form
bonding in the form of an alcohol
or a double bonded O, there are many
different structures that do contain
that double bonded oxygen shape.
Typically, you will always see that C
double bond O um, written like right.
Like so where all of a sudden you
have that vertical point right in the
middle where it's showing a carbon.
Uh, you might also see them on ring
structures or on cyclic compounds too.
They don't always necessarily need
to be in one way, but ketones are
always in the middle of a chain.
So keep that mind.
It looks more like it's the key
to unlocking the whole chain.
It has to be in the middle of the chain.
Our next example is an aldehyde.
Notice how this looks
very similar to a ketone.
The previous example showed that
when we had a ketone, it looked like
this, where we have C double bonded
O with an R group on both sides.
Now the difference between the ketone and
the aldehyde is all lies on that hydrogen
that is connected at neck to our carbon.
So we gotta pay attention that if
you see a hydrogen attached, this
has to be on the end of a chain.
It has, uh, several different
properties and its reactivity changes.
When you have that hydrogen
located only at the end.
So if we were to show some of these
different structures, generally we
have that C double bond o written
right at the end of a structure.
Um, or it's as an offshoot or a
branch onto on a cyclic, cyclic
compound as well With carboxylic
acids, what sets us apart is that
now we have two different functional
groups attached to the same carbon.
So notice how you have that c
double bonded O, also the O.
So whenever we have the seed double
bonded oxygens that are here it you, it's
something that when you have them attached
to a structure, make sure you look.
On both sides of the carbon
to see what is attached to it.
As I will commonly say throughout these
videos, as you're crossing the street
and as if the C double bond O is your
street, you wanna look both ways.
In this case, you see that
o h that is attached here.
This is your acidic property.
So if you think of lemons or
oranges or anything that is acidic
in a lot of our foods, this is
what is responsible for those.
So for a common example of this
is, let's say if I do CH three.
C double bond O with an OH.
This is acetic acid, so,
or also known as vinegar.
This is also something that has
to be on the end of a chain.
Next functional group is Esther's
ether's all, as you can see here.
Have that C double bond O, and also
have an auction next to 'em as well.
But it's being linked by a rest
of the molecule R on both sides.
So it does not, once again, does
not have to be the exact same thing,
but there's gonna be an al alcohol
chain on both sides of the molecule.
So let's say if I have, uh, this structure
here with that O, with another O, Here.
This is an example of an ester.
Now, esters are something that is
something that you're gonna smell.
They're typically found in perfumes,
colognes of fruits, for example, thing.
Flowers.
They're responsible for a lot
of aromas that you will commonly
come across in everyday life.
The next one, these are
referred to as amines.
Amine the way to think about this is
think of the word minimum, meaning that
we have the minimum number of attachments
on it compared to the next one, which
is going to be amides, which have that
C double bonded O, but with a means.
The big thing is nitrogen,
if you can remember how it
can form up to three bonds.
So on this you can see that we have
our first example of an amine, which
is typically, uh, very commonly
written as R-NH2 as our group.
Now, depending on the type of amine,
this is referred to as a primary amine,
where it's only attached to one R group.
The other ones you can see it's
attached to two R groups, and then
three R groups is the other types.
So we have primary, secondary,
tertiary, which we will cover in
other videos as well, um, which is
all about how many different carbons
can they possibly be attached to.
Now our next example, which
is a amines, they look a lot
different than before amides.
You can see how that C
double bonded oxygen.
Here, right, so it's crossing that street
and looking both sides before crossing.
We can see that we add another
piece to it, making a lot more
complicated than in amine, right?
Amine, as I mentioned, has the minimum
number of pieces, is how we can remember
that, where it only has that one single
R group that is attached to it, compared
to in amide has a double bonded oxygen.
So to show some examples of both amines
and amides, it's the same general idea
that if we want to show that structure,
we can show our amide here, and it can
also attach just very similar to an Ester.
Um, when it comes to a means,
this is when we have our NH2.
Attached at the end.
It could be in the middle of a chain.
It could link things together
because it can make those three
bonds around the nitrogen.
That's very different.
The means and the mines tend to be
very means are very smelly compounds.
They typically smell like fish.
The mines are actually one of the
leading, uh, bonds that you'll find
in protein chains behind peptides.
So they're a very important part
into biochemistry and under by
understanding biological function.
Our last functional group is a fennel
group or also known as an aromatic ring.
So with an aromatic ring, you can
notice that it has three alternating
double bonds within the structure,
which I'm high here in blue.
Uh, this is also very commonly
known as a benzene ring.
So if we ever see that compound where
we have the benzene ring here, that
is a very specific and special shape.
We will talk about in future videos of
how aromatics are extremely stable groups.
Benzines are commonly used in
pharmaceutical compounds to help
stabilize a structure so that way
it is able to actually help your
body and to survive a long time to
deliver its effects in the body.
So, Let's now go through some
common examples that you will see
in your organic chemistry course.
It's very common that you will have
to identify different functional
groups, um, within compounds.
So if we had the following molecule
here, and I ask you, okay, let's
go through trying to identify
the different functional groups.
And you can see there are many.
Um, the first one that if we can
quickly notice is, uh, right over here.
So we have an ether compound.
We also have some others as well.
Uh, if we have the one over here,
we notice that we have an alcohol.
And then as we kind of go through
this compound as well, we can
see that we have some others.
Uh, we have over here you have that C
double bonded O, which if you kind of
go through your notes and look, you're
trying to think like, OH, which one is it?
'cause remember, it's all about crossing
the street before you go across.
With this one, it is a very common
error that students will make.
This one is an aldehyde.
Um, with this, what do I
mean by a common error?
Well being that we see it's on the
side of the chain, we can remember
that we can fill in a hydrogen here.
Remember four bonds for every one
of these carbons that we have.
So let's say if I highlight the carbon
here in green and we can zoom in on that.
Well, we can count the
number of bonds, right?
We have 1, 2, 3, 4 bonds
all around that structure.
So there's a hydrogen there,
so that is an aldehyde.
Now, what else is there in the structure?
There might be one other, you might
see your big aromatic group as well,
which is the ring structure here.
So that is your phenyl group, which
is a part of your ring as well.
So those are all the different types.
Let's go into a common, another common
mistake and problem that students make for
identifying their functional groups, which
is so important for your organic course.
Okay?
This example, once again,
identify the functional groups.
Now with these, what a lot of students
do is they make common mistakes that
identify groups that they see right away.
Make sure you look at everything
connected to it, because it could
be a slightly different example.
So for example, right here I see
that, oh, I have an alcohol group
that is attached to this ring.
We have an oh, which makes perfect sense.
However, one thing that you can quickly
notice is that there is a C double
bond O that is right next to it.
We have to look at the
entire structure all around.
This is a much larger group here.
This is a carboxylic acid.
Whenever we have c double bonded
o's look on both sides of the
street before crossing, right?
So when we have that carbon, we're
gonna look to left, look to the right,
see if there's anything near it.
And you should do this for the all
functional groups because they could
have an altered identity because of that.
So that is a carboxylic acid.
What else do we have?
Over here?
We see an NH2, right?
So that is something different.
Now the question, is it
a mean or is it an aide?
A mean is the minimum configuration.
So we only see an NH two connect
to the rest of the chain.
So this is an amine group.
Our next portion over on the far
side, we have this over here, which
is referring to an alcohol, right?
And then we also once again
have our benzene structure.
So we have, we highlight the ring here.
We can see that we have a benzene or an
aromatic, also known as a phenyl group.
And that is our, is,
that is our last part.
So we have all those little pieces.
Let's try another, which you're
more than welcome to pause the
video and try yourself and see if
you can try to identify all the
functional groups on this compound.
Now when we look at this,
the first thing is, is I, I
notice is this C double bond O.
That is right here on the
side of the structure.
Now the thing with the C double
bonded O is trying to figure
out exactly which one is it.
Now this, we can see that well,
we're missing one bond here
and it has a hydrogen there.
So remember we always
count to four, right?
How do I see the four?
Well, we have our hydrogen here.
We have the single bonded carbon
to carbon bond, and then we have
one part of the double bond.
The second part of the double bond, right?
Those four colors all represent
the four bonds that are here,
um, in this particular group.
So this is what is representing
and aldehyde, right?
So that is our group here.
So let's label that now.
What other groups do I have?
Well, I also have another group
that looks very similar to that.
I have C double bonded O over here,
but this is an example of a ketone that
is on the other side of the structure.
And then the last group is an alcohol.
Now, last thing is what
a common mistake is.
Is this a fennel group?
There's a ring here.
However, it's missing a key
piece, like the one above.
One above had those
alternating double bonds.
This doesn't exist here.
So this is just a normal ring
or cyclic compound versus the as
cyclic that we talked about in
part one, which is just a chain.
So there's different types of
chains and organic hydrocarbons
that we are going to see.
So this is the end of our second
part of just setting that language.
There will be many videos to come for
chemistry for these types of introductory,
organic, and biochemistry videos.
To help our Allied Health Sciences better
master these or this course and all your
courses that you are taking out there
on out there in the internet world.
This has been Dr.
Dan.
I hope this video helped, and please
hit that like and subscribe button
to see future videos out there.
All right, I'll see you all later.
Bye now.